<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ceremonies, solemnities, and prayers, vsed at the opening of the holy gates of foure churches, within the citie of Rome, in the yere of Iubile and also the great Iubile for this yeere of our Lord 1600. graunted by Pope Clement the eight, that now is; together with the bull of the said Pope Clement, made touching the Iubile, for all those that shall visite the great churches of S. Peter, S. Paul, S. Iohn de Latran, and S. Marie maior, in the citie of Rome, this present yeere of our Lord 1600. aforesaid.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110720</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846210</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846210</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11024)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 394:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ceremonies, solemnities, and prayers, vsed at the opening of the holy gates of foure churches, within the citie of Rome, in the yere of Iubile and also the great Iubile for this yeere of our Lord 1600. graunted by Pope Clement the eight, that now is; together with the bull of the said Pope Clement, made touching the Iubile, for all those that shall visite the great churches of S. Peter, S. Paul, S. Iohn de Latran, and S. Marie maior, in the citie of Rome, this present yeere of our Lord 1600. aforesaid.</title>
                  <author>Catholic Church.</author>
                  <author>Catholic Church. Pope (1592-1605 : Clement VIII). Annus Domini placabilis. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By S. Stafford] for Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holy Year, 1600 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11161:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11161:1"/>
            <p>The Ceremonies, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, and prayers, vſed at the opening of the holy gates of foure Churches, within the Citie of Rome, in the yere of Iubile:</p>
            <p>And alſo the great Iubile for this yeere of our Lord 1600. graunted by Pope Clement the eight, that now is;</p>
            <p>Together with the Bull of the ſaid Pope Clement, made touching the Iubile, for all thoſe that ſhall viſite the great Churches of S. Peter, S. Paul, S. Iohn de Latran, and S. Marie <hi>maior,</hi> in the Citie of Rome, this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent yeere of our Lord 1600. aforeſaid.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>IHS</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d at London for Iohn Wolfe. 1600.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:11161:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:11161:2"/>
            <head>The ceremonies, ſolemnities and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vſed at opening of the holy gates of fowre Churches, within the Citie of Rome, in the yeere of Iubile.</head>
            <head type="sub">And firſt, the opening of the gate of the Church of Saint Peter in Vatican.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the 24. day of the moneth of December, being the vigill of the birth of Chriſt (commonly called Chriſtmas day) after dinner, about Euening, our holy Father the Pope, apparelled in his Pontificalibus, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with my Lords the Cardinals, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, eche man clothed according to their dignities &amp; degrees, the Officers appointed for the purpoſe, marching all in proceſsion, and the Croſſe borne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, went to the Chappell of the Apoſtolical palace, where our holy Father falling vpon his knees before the holy Sacrament, with the reſt of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, made their praiers; in the meane time, certaine
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11161:3"/>candels were lighted, and giuen vnto my Lords the Cardinals, Prelats, and Officers, the Cardinals can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels being white wax, and waying three pounds, the Prelats and Officers candels of common wax, each, ſix ounces the peece. There, our holy Father being ſtill on his knees, powred incenſe vpon the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: which done, they began to ſing, <hi>Veni crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſpiritus:</hi> which Hymne the Quiriſters continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the proceſsion began to march out of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, to goe to Saint Peters Church, our holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being borne in his Chaire to the gate of the ſaid Church, the ſaid gate being walled vp, and all the reſt of the gates ſhut; where being arriued, our holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſcended out of his Chaire, with a wax candel burning in his hand, went vp into an other higher ſeate then the firſt, prepared for the purpoſe, hard by the ſaid holy gate, in the which Chaire he ſat down, and hauing reſted for a time, he deſcended, and with a hammer appointed for the purpoſe, hee ſtrooke three blowes vpon the gate, pronouncing theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes following three times; vnto each of the ſaid ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Quiriſters anſwering as followeth:</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Aperite mihi por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Iuſtitiae.</label>
                     <item>Lord open vnto mee the gates of Iuſtice.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Et ingreſſus in eas, conſitebor Domino.</label>
                     <item>And being entred ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I will praiſe the Lord.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:11161:3"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Introibo in domum tuam, Domine.</label>
                     <item>Lord, I will goe into thy houſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Adorabo ad tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum ſanctum tuum in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more tuo</label>
                     <item>And will worſhip in thy holy Temple, with feare and trembling.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Aperite mihi por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, quoniam nobiſcum Deus.</label>
                     <item>Open the gates, for God is with vs.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Quiafecit virtutem in Iſrael.</label>
                     <item>Becauſe he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his glorie in Iſrael.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Which done, our holy Father returning to his Chaire, ſaid,</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Domine exaudi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem meam.</label>
                     <item>Lord, heare my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Et clamor meus ad te veniet.</label>
                     <item>And my crie ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vp vnto thee.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>And being in his Chaire, the Maſons and other workmen with their tooles, breake downe the wall of the ſaid holy gate, and the Pope continuing his praiers, ſaid,</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Dominus vobiſcum.</label>
                     <item>The Lord be with you.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Et cum ſpiritu tuo.</label>
                     <item>And with thy ſpirite.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11161:4"/>
            <sp>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Oremus.</label>
                     <item>Let vs pray.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>Oratio.</stage>
               <p>ACtiones noſtras quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus, Domine, aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando praeueni, &amp; adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uando proſequere, vt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta noſtra oratio &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio a te ſemper incipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, &amp; per te coepta finia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, per Chriſtum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum noſtrum.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>The praier.</stage>
               <p>LOrd, we pray thee, to inſpire vs in our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and aſsiſt vs in our waies, to the end that all our words and workes may begin, continue, and end in thee, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Which prayer being ended, the Quiriſters ſung the Pſalme, <hi>Iubilate Deo omnis terra &amp;c.</hi> Let all the inhabitants of the earth reioyce in the Lord, &amp;c. With other Canticles of praiſe and thankes giuing.</p>
            <p>In the meane time the ſaid workmen and all the people, moued with deuotion, tooke and bare away the ſtones and morter of the ſaid gate, with ſo great diligence, and dexteritie, that all whatſoeuer was found (great or little) were voyded from thence, (as it may be ſaid) in the twinckling of an eye; the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries apparrelled in their habites and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, waſhing the poſts of the ſaid holy gate, with holy water.</p>
            <p>Which holy gate being opened, and the ſtones borne away, as afore ſaid, our holy Father the Pope,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11161:4"/>before he entered, ſaid the verſicles folowing, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the Quiriſters anſwered.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Haec eſt dies quam fecit Dominus.</label>
                     <item>Behold the day which the Lord hath made.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Exultemus &amp; lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temur in ea.</label>
                     <item>Let vs bee glad, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce therein.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Beatus populus tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Domine.</label>
                     <item>Lord, thy people are happie and bleſſed.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Qui ſcit Iubilatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem?</label>
                     <item>Who can declare their gladnes?</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Haec eſt porta Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</label>
                     <item>Behold, the gate of the Lord.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Iuſti intrabunt in eam.</label>
                     <item>The Iuſt ſhall enter therein.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Domine, exaudi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem meam.</label>
                     <item>Lord, heare my praier.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Clamor meus ad te veniat.</label>
                     <item>And my crie ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vnto thee.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>V.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Dominus vobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</label>
                     <item>The Lorde bee with you.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Et cum ſpiritu tuo.</label>
                     <item>And with thy ſpirit.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Oremus.</label>
                     <item>Let vs pray.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>Oratio.</stage>
               <p>DEus, qui per Moyſem famulum tuum populo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11161:5"/>Iſraelitico annum Iobelei, &amp; remiſsionis inſtituiſti, concede propitius nobis famulis tuis Iobelei annum hunc tua auctoritate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum, quo portam hanc populo tuo ad preces tuae maieſtati porrigendas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grediente ſolenniter ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riri voluiſti foeliciter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choare vt in eo venia at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que indulgentia plenae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsionis omnium delicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum obtenta, cum dies noſtrae aduocationis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenerit, ad coeleſtem glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam perfruendam tuae miſericordiae munere per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducamur, per Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:11161:4"/>
               <stage>The praier.</stage>
               <p>O Lord, who by thy ſeruant Moyſes did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11161:5"/>ordaine and appoint for thy people of Iſrael, the yeere of Iubile, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſinnes, graunt vs thy grace, and to al thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that we may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily beginne this preſent yeere of Iubile ordained by thee, and wherein thy pleaſure is, that this gate ſhould with al ſolemnitie be opened vnto thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to enter, and preſent our praiers vnto thee, to the end, that in this yeere, hauing obtained full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion &amp; pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al our ſinnes, that when the day, wherin it ſhal pleaſe thee to take vs out of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie world, ſhall come, we may by thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, enter into thy glorie, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:11161:5"/>
            <p>This prayer ended, the croſſe is giuen vnto our holy father, who kneeling before the holy gate, beginneth to ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Te Deum laudamus &amp;c.</hi> Lord, wee praiſe thy holy name. And being entred by the ſaid gate into the church, the Queriſters ſang the reſt of the ſaid Hymne, vnto the end. Our holy father being ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he aſcended againe vnto his chaire, wherein he was borne by the officers (thereunto appointed) to the high altar of the ſaid church of S. Peter: and there deſcending out of his chaire, he praied before the altar: which praier being ended, he aſcended into an other ſeate higher, and more eleuated, where for a time hauing reſted himſelfe, he ſtood vp, and began Euening praier, rehearſing the Natiuity of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, as the maner is.</p>
            <p>Vpon the ſame day, and at the like howre, three of my Lordes the Cardinals went vnto the other three holy gates, of the three churches, of S. Paul, S. Iohn de Latran, S. Mary maior.</p>
            <p>Which Cardinals, at euery of the ſaid churches, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame ceremonies, and like praiers aforeſaid, opened the gates of the ſaid three Churches.</p>
            <p>Al the ſaid gates of S. Peter, S. Paul, S. Iohn de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tran, &amp; S. Mary maior, remaine open, from the ſame day, vntill the end of the ſame yeere, and ſo continew
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11161:6"/>euery yeere of Iubile, to the end that al faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may therein continually obtaine pardon and full remiſsion of their ſinnes, to the praiſe, and glory of God and all his holy Church. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>The Bull of our holy Father, (by the grace of God) Clement the eight, made touching <hi>the Iubile, for all thoſe that shall viſit the great</hi> Churches of S. Peter, S. Paul, S. Iohn de Latran, and Saint Mary Maior, in the Citie of Rome, in the yeere of our Lord 1600.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Lement Biſhop, and ſeruant of the ſeruants of God, to all faithfull Chriſtians, to whome theſe letters ſhall come, greeting, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Apoſtolicall benediction.</p>
            <p>Dearely beloued children in Ieſus Chriſt, at this preſent (by the grace of God) appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the placable yeere of our Lorde, the yeere of remiſsion and pardon; now commeth the acceptable time, and the daies of eternall ſaluation beginne to approch for the redemption of mens ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ſaluation of their ſoules. Behold, not farre hence, the yeere of Iubile, ſo much pleaſing and wiſhed for by all Chriſtians, which is the 1600. yeere, from the moſt bleſſed child-bearing of (the holy mother of God) Marie the Virgin, the which wee meane to celebrate, according to the auncient cuſtome, with ioy, and aſſembly of the faithfull, in this our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble City of Rome; and with ſo much the more ioy, becauſe the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11161:6"/>ſayd yeere formally, and with efficacie, repreſenteth the firſt originall of the ſame: for as it is well known by old traditions, and monuments of our aunceſtors, agreeing and conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the moſt auncient inſtitutions of the Church of Rome, as the yeeres and times paſſe and come to an ende, that is, that euerie hundreth yeere, from the birth of our Lord and Sauior Ieſus Chriſt, there were moſt large indulgences, pronounced vnto all ſuch as deuoutly ſhall viſite the moſt holy and ſacred Churches of the moſt bleſſed Apoſtles: &amp; certainly, this moſt ancient inſtitution, of celebrating the 100. yeere within the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Rome, extracted (not from a vaine ſuperſtition of the Gentiles, but proceeding from a pure zeale &amp; deuotion, with a great concurrence and aſſembly of the Chriſtians) hath bene confirmed by Pope Boniface the 8. of happy memory, by his Apoſtolicall decree, not onely for an aſſurance to all thoſe of our age, but alſo a perpetuall memory in time to come. And although other Popes our predeceſſors, ſuch as ſucceeded him, reſtrayned the time of celebrating the Iubile to a ſhorter number of yeeres, becauſe of the breuity of mans life: yet this cuſtome of the celebration of the 100. yeere, is by good right, of more auctority in regard of the auncient tradition and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thereof: And in truth, it ſeemeth to be wrought by the ſecrete counſel of GOD, that in the laſt yeere of euery age, (which commonly in theſe daies is accounted the longeſt time of mans life,) all Chriſtians ingenerall ſhould (euen in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fortreſſe, and houſe of Chriſtian religion) reiterate ſo great a benefit, which is, that Ieſus Chriſt the brightneſſe of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, by whom all mankind hath receyued ſaluation, was borne of a virgin; and alſo, that all Chriſtians ſhould like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe repaire vnto the ſeat of the holy Apoſtle S. Peter, and to the ſtone and foundation of the faith, as children to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and ſheep to their ſoueraine paſtor: And further, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may euidently behold the perſit vnity of a troup of ſheep and their paſtour, and that the brightnes of one vniuerſal faith doth ſhine and giue light into all places, which faith hath neuer
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11161:7"/>changed, nor bin altered by any ende or alterations of times, but ſtill by an inuiolable confeſsion, hath continued whole and intire among the faithfull, without any corruption; and alſo that the world might know, that the members are more ſtraightly bounde and vnited vnto their viſible head, by the gluing and bandes of faith and charitie, and that in the ende, the ſame Spirit, by the which the onely Catholike Church and her body, is miraculouſly conioyned and vnited togither, may be euidently manifeſted, then when as in the ſaid Church of Rome, the mother of vnitie is celebrated (as if all the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were aſſembled) with all deuotion and ſolemne ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, of a whole yeere vpon certaine dayes appoynted, which by good right is called the holy yeere.</p>
            <p>Now this holy yeere, a yeere agreeable to the Lord, and ſuch a yeere, as appeaſeth his wrath, a yeere wherein men may doe penance, and be perfectly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted from the bottome of their hearts, vnto the Lord the father of mercie, was firſt denounced vnto the world by Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of GOD, the true author both of our liues and ſaluations, whom the Father hath anoynted with the holy Ghoſt; and hauing powred vpon him all fulneſſe of grace, ſent him to preach vnto the poore, to ayde the humble, to eaſe the heauie hearted, to preach indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and remiſsion vnto thoſe that were captiue, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance vnto priſoners, and to open the way vnto the blinde. We likewiſe, who (although abiects and vnworthy) by diuine diſpoſition, doe exerciſe the place of Vicars to Ieſus Chriſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, ſitting in the higheſt ſentinell of the Apoſtolicall watch-tower, to announce, declare, and preach the ſame yere of Iubile, of true repentaunce, and ſpirituall comfort, vnto all you that are faythfull Chriſtians in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And for that the charitie of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, for whom wee exerciſe the charge and embaſſage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Nations, doth entice vs, the zeale of the ſaluation of mens ſoules touching our hearts, we exhort and deſire euery man in generall, by the vertue of the bloud which Chriſt hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11161:7"/>ſhed, and by his holy comming, as alſo by the name of the day, wherein he ſhall ſit as a terrible Iudge, that euerie one of you, eſpecially in this time of Iubile, withdrawe himſelfe from his euill wayes, and returne vnto the Lorde, with a pure and ſincere heart, a good conſcience, and an vnfained heart, becauſe our GOD is gentle and mercifull, full of compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and one that deferreth the puniſhing of all thoſe that are true repentants.</p>
            <p>But in the meane time, that with great ioy, according to our paſtorall office, wee call and inuite our wel-beloued ſon in Ieſus Chriſt, the Emperor, Kings, and Catholike Princes, &amp; all other faithfull Chriſtians throughout all the world, and namely, ſuch as inhabite the prouinces and Regions furtheſt diſtant, vnto that moſt agreeable celebration of this Iubile: wee are in a manner pricked with an extreame dolour and greefe, calling to minde howe many great Nations and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of people are moſt miſerably cutte off and diſioyned from the vnitie and communion of the Catholike and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall Church, who in the precedent hundreth yeeres, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching with vs in one Catholike and Apoſtolike Church, with one will and conſent, in this houſe of our Lord, haue celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with great ioy and ſpirituall exaltation, the holy yeere of the ſayde Iubile, for whom wee would moſt willingly loſe our liues, and ſheade our heart blouds (if neede were) to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the eternall ſaluation of their ſoules. In the meane time, you our obedient children, and true Catholikes, come, mount vp into this place which God hath choſen, come to the Spirituall Sion, and the holy Ieruſalem, not by letter, but by Spirite, from whence, from the beginning and Originall of the Church, the law of God, and the truth of the Goſpel hath ſpred it ſelfe throughout all the Nations and parts of the earth. This is the happie Citie, the fayth whereof, is commended to all the worlde, hauing beene commended by the mouth of the Apoſtle, wherein the moſt happie Apoſtles, Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Saint Paul, haue both preached their doctrine, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11161:8"/>ſhed their blood, to the ende that being made the head of all the world by the ſacred ſeat of S. Peter, it ſhould be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all beleeuers, and miſtreſſe of all other Churches. Here is the ſtone of faith, here is the fountaine of ſacerdotall vnity, here is the doctrine of pure verity, here are the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, and the ſoueraigne powre to bind and vnbinde; and to conclude, here is the treaſure of the Church, full of ſacred Indulgences, neuer able to be diminiſhed, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Biſhop of Rome is Gardian, and diſpenſator, who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributeth them at all times, when he knoweth by the ſecret will of God, that it is requiſite, but ſpecially, in the yeere of the holy Iubile he inlargeth, and beſtoweth them, with a moſt holy and liberall hand, then when the holy gates of the moſt auncient, and moſt religious temples, and Churches of this noble Citie, are opened by ſolemne ceremonies, and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, purged of the ſpottes and fowleneſſe of their ſinnes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ioyfully before the face of the Lord, no more vnto the end that according to the precepts of the old law, (which onely had the ſhadowe of goodneſſe to come,) nor according to the cuſtome of the Hebrewes, to whome all things were ſet downe by figure, or els as bondſlaues, tied vnder the yoke of humane ſeruitude, in becomming free, or as priſoners detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in priſons, are releaſed, or as ſuch as are charged with great dettes, are acquited, whereby they may reenter into the lands and poſſeſsions of their aunceſtors; for all theſe terreſtriall things are tranſitory &amp; not permanent: but the fruites of the holy yeere of our Iubile are moſt fruitfull and aboundant, that is, that mens ſoules, redeemed by the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, are deliuered from the inſupportable yoke of diabolicall tyranny, and from the obſcure priſon and chaines of ſinne, by the diuine vertue of the Sacraments, and their ſinnes and puniſhments being remitted, they are adopted ſonnes of God, and admitted to the heritage of the heauenly kingdome, and poſſeſsion of Paradiſe, receyuing other infinite benefites of God.</p>
            <p>We therefore, following the paths and footeſteps of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11161:8"/>Biſhops, our predeceſſors, &amp; obſeruing their deuout, and moſt holy inſtitution, with the conſent of our moſt reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend brethren the Cardinals of the holy Church of Rome, and by the authoritie of the moſt puiſſant God, &amp; of the moſt bleſſed Apoſtles, Saint Peter and Saint Paul, as alſo by our owne, with as much ſpirituall reioycing as poſsibly wee may, to the glorie of God, and exaltation of the Catholike Church, do publiſh and ſignifie vnto all men, the celebration of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, in this yeere, being the yeere of our Lord 1600. to begin at the euening of the Vigill of the Natiuitie of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, of the ſame yeere of 1600. and to continue for the ſpace of one whole yeere then next enſuing: in the which yeere of Iubile, we in mercy and compaſsion in our Lord, giue and grant free indulgence, remiſsion and pardon of all ſinnes, to all the faithfull in Ieſus Chriſt, without exception of perſon, who being truely repentant and confeſſed, ſhall deuoutly viſit the chiefe Churches of the bleſſed Apoſtles, Saint Peter and Saint Paul, as alſo thoſe of Saint Iohn de Latran, &amp; Saint Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Maior, within the citie of Rome, once in a day, for the ſpace of thirtie dayes following, or otherwiſe, if they be Romanes or inhabitants of the Citie, or for the ſpace of fifteene dayes, if they be pilgrims, or other ſtrangers, vpon condition that they ſhall make humble prayers vnto God, for the ſaluation of all the faithful and al Chriſtian people: and becauſe it may fal out, that among ſuch, as by reaſon of this Iubile, ſhall haue enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed this iourney, or that are arriued in this Citie of Rome, ſome being let or hindred by the way, or otherwiſe within this Citie, by ſickneſſe, or ſome other lawfull impeachment, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euented by death, cannot effect theſe things, and viſite the Churches and Temples aforeſayd, not hauing accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the dayes limited, or otherwiſe haue not begunne them; wee, as much as poſſible wee may, beningly deſiring to fauour their deuoutneſſe, will, that ſuch people being truely repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and confeſſed, ſhall all bee made participants of this our indulgence and remiſsion, as if they had effectually viſited the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:11161:9"/>ſaid Churches and Temples of Rome, vpon the daies by vs preſcribed.</p>
            <p>And you our Reuerend brethren, Patriarches, Primates, Archbiſhops, &amp; Biſhops, which partly at our requeſt are ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned and called hereunto, you that are guides, &amp; Paſtors of the people, the light of the world, and the ſalt of the earth, take into your hands the tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pets of ſiluer, which you muſt vſe in this yeere of Iubile, that is to ſay; preach the word of God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, annou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce this ioy vnto the people, that they may be ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; that by the ayd of Gods diuine grace, they may be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to receiue the celeſtiall benefits, which God, the giuer of al good things, by our weake miniſtery hath prepared for all his deere &amp; wel-beloued children; draw your brethren by words, &amp; the ſimple &amp; vnlearned by good examples, bringing them vnto the pappes of this their moſt deere mother, that hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten them in Ieſus Chriſt: bring the children to their father, the ſheep to their ſoueraigne paſtor, the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers to their head, the faithful to the ſtone and foundation of the faith, wherein al the edificy &amp; building of the Chriſtian church is erected: bring the people to the holy Church of Rome, and to the glorious Princes of the earth, S. Peter &amp; S. Paul, which taught the law of God throughout all the world, as alſo the faith; whoſe digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and authority is as yet extant and in force in their vnworthy ſucceſſor. Call therfore the aſſembly vnto theſe ſacred Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, that they may receiue the ſalutary fruits thereof, in this Citie of Rome: aſſemble the people, ſanctifie the Church, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the ſheep committed to your charge, becauſe we are but ſtrangers and pilgrims here in this life, hauing no permanent place, but ſeeke for that which is to come.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the dayes of this our troubleſome and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pilgrimage are but ſhort, and for that we know not when the maſter of the family, &amp; our eſpouſe Ieſus Chriſt will come, warne them, that for this cauſe they will be watchfull, &amp; beare in their hands burning lampes, filled with the oyle of loue and charity, and that they make haſt to enter into this reſt: for if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11161:9"/>euer they had cauſe, it is now, that for the loue of Ieſus Chriſt, they ſhould abandon and leaue off al wrath, riots, debates, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and inueterated enmities: it is now time that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ought to haue pity vpon their conſeruators, to the end that our moſt mercifull God may freely forgiue them all their ſinnes; it is at this time, that we muſt ſpecially purge and clenſe our ſelues of all the impurities of the fleſh, to the end that the Temple of God may be pure and cleane, and that euery man may haue his earthly veſſell laden with honour, and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; ſo God may dwell within their bodies. To conclude, we muſt wholy exterminate and abandon all theftes, robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, homicides, adulteries, and all other ſinnes, to the end that the wrath of God may be appeaſed, and that thoſe that attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto themſelues the name of Chriſtians, may by him be accounted and holden for true Chriſtians, imitators of Ieſus Chriſt, and folowers of good workes. Teach them then, how they ought, with a contrite heart, and humble ſpirit, to prepare themſelues by continuall praiers, faſtings, and other workes of mercy, to merite and obtaine theſe ſalutary indulgences, and that thoſe that are indued with the riches of this world, ſhould open their hearts, and by that meanes relieuing the neceſsity of their poore brethren, and that before all other things, they extend their mercifull charity vnto ſuch pilgrims, as ſhall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to Rome, renewing with ſpirituall ioy, the holy hoſpitality agreeable and pleaſing vnto God, which by the moſt aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chriſtians in times paſt (euen in the middle of all ſtormes, tempeſts and perſecutions) hath with great diligence bene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued &amp; kept: aduertiſe them alſo, that they pray for all kings, and Chriſtian princes, that we may liue in peace and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and that peace may perpetually be kept and obſerued.</p>
            <p>To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, teach them with what modeſty, with what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; with what brotherly loue, they are to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues knowne, when as they ſhall once haue enterpriſed the holy viage, to the end that, in all places they may yeeld the ſweet ſauour of Ieſus Chriſt. Shew your ſelues alſo, my reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11161:10"/>and all the Clergie, to be the example of all good works, and the formality of the troupe, to the end that all others may be conſerued, as it were, by the ſalt of your vertues, &amp; religion, and abhorre all filthines of ſinne, &amp; that in the end, all we with full conſent and agreement, in one ſpirit of Chriſtian charity, with all holines and righteouſnes may ſerue God.</p>
            <p>We alſo exhort and deſire, in the name of God, our moſt deare ſonnes in Ieſus Chriſt, the Emperour, kings, &amp; all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Princes, that ſeeing they haue receiued diuers and moſt great benefits, of him, by whom all Kings do raigne, with ſo much the more ardency, as reaſon requireth, they ſhould be ſtirred vp with a great and good zeale, to procure the glory of God; and before al things, that they comfort and ayd the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vigilancy of our brethren, the Biſhops, and other ſuperiour Prelates, charging their Magiſtrates and Officers to further &amp; aſsiſt them, to the end that the vnbridled liberty of the wicked may be reſtrained, and the intentions of honeſt men by their royall ayd and fauour relieued &amp; ſuſtained: and ſpecially, that they vſe their beneuolence and charity towards pilgrimes, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing order, that they may ſafely paſſe along the way, and by no meanes be impeached by the wicked and peruerſe genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that being louingly receiued into the publike hoſpitals, and by that meanes comforted, and relieued with all things neceſſary for their viages, they may ioyfully without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion purſue, and end their iourney taken in hand, &amp; ſo returne into their owne countreis: for by theſe offerings, kings and Princes ſhall pleaſe God, to the end they may liue long and in all happines vpon the earth, and that at the laſt they may be receyued into the eternall tabernacles, by the ſame poore and miſerable people, to whome they ſhall haue exerciſed their charities, which are thoſe in whoſe bodies Ieſus Chriſt is nouriſhed and fedde.</p>
            <p>And to the ende that this our preſent Bull may with more eaſe fall into the hands of all the faithful, whereſoeuer they be, our pleaſure is, that to the copies hereof being imprinted, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11161:10"/>with the hand of a publike notary, and ſealed with the ſeale of ſome man of Eccleſiaſticall authoritie, the like credite ſhall be giuen, as vnto theſe, being the originall. Let no man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ſo fooliſh-hardy to infringe or gaine-ſay this our Bull of Indiction, promulgation, confeſsion, impartition, exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, prayer, and will: and if any man be ſo bolde to attempt it, let him knowe that hee ſhall incurre the indignation of God, and of his moſt bleſſed Apoſtles S. Peter and S. Paul. Giuen at Rome in the Church of Saint Peter, in the yeere of the incarnation of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt 1599. the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of May, and in the eight yeere of our Pontificate.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed <hi>B. Dat. Marcellus Veſtrius Barbianus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>Regiſtred by Marcellus the Secretarie.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>A. de Alexis.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
